Allen W Zhang | Curriculum Vitae

☐ +1 917 913 1779 • ☑ allenz9410[at]gmail.com • ☐ Irrationone

MD/PhD Candidate at the University of British Columbia, BC Cancer, and Centre for Molecular Medicine and Therapeutics (CMMT), currently based at Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center. Bioinformatics researcher and Vanier scholar with interests in cancer immunology, single cell transcriptomics, ovarian cancer, and machine learning.

Previous Employment

Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center

New York, USA

Graduate Research Assistant, Shah Lab

September 2018-present

I am undertaking a research exchange during my MD/PhD degree to acquire experience conducting clinical trials analysis in ovarian cancer immunotherapy.

BC Cancer Vancouver, Canada

MD/PhD Student, Shah and Wasserman Labs

May 2015-present

I am working on projects in cancer immunology and genomics, primarily in the context of ovarian cancer, using whole-genome sequencing, single cell transcriptomics, histologic image analysis, TCR- and BCR-sequencing, immunohistochemistry, and mutation signature analysis.

Armstrong Lab Vancouver, Canada

Work Learn Student

September 2015-May 2016

I developed a genetics module on cancer exome analysis for UBC Medical School's curriculum renewal with Dr. Linlea Armstrong.

Centre for Molecular Medicine and Therapeutics

Vancouver, Canada

Bioinformatics Analyst, Wasserman Lab

September 2012-August 2013

Developed software for transcription factor binding site prediction (MANTA) and the 2014 release of JASPAR, the largest freely-accessible database of high-quality transcription factor binding sites.

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, Canada

NSERC Summer Student, Wasserman Lab

May 2012-August 2012

Developed fast computational methods for identification of transcription factor binding sites in whole-genome sequence data.

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, Canada

Work Learn Student, Centre for the Culture of Microorganisms

May 2011-August 2011

Helped grow various single- and multicellular microorganisms for UBC Biology.

Education

Academic Qualifications.....

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, Canada

MD/PhD Candidate, Bioinformatics, GPA: 97%

2014–present

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, Canada

MD Candidate

2013-2014

University of British Columbia

Combined Honours, Computer Science and Biology, GPA: 95.3%

University of British Columbia

Science One, GPA: 96%, Top Student

University Transition Program

GPA: 97%, Top Male Graduate

Vancouver, Canada 2010–2013

....................................

Vancouver, Canada

2010–2011

Vancouver, Canada

2008-2010

Notable Projects....

o MD/PhD Project (Ongoing): 'CellAssign: Computational identification of known cell types in single cell transcriptome data using marker genes'

I am developing a Bayesian model for probabilistically assigning cells in single cell RNA-seq data to known cell types based on marker genes.

• MD/PhD Project: 'Interfaces of malignant and immunologic clonal dynamics in high-grade serous ovarian cancer'

I led a multi-national collaboration to establish the evolutionary interplay between lymphocytes and tumour cells in high-grade serous ovarian cancer by multimodal data analysis. Integrating whole-genome sequencing analysis of clonal composition, histologic imaging data, immunohistochemistry measurements, T- and B-cell receptor sequencing, and mutational signature analysis, we reported an evolutionary interplay between the immune microenvironment and tumour clones in *Cell* (senior authors: Dr. Sohrab Shah and Dr. Brad Nelson). I was responsible for co-ordinating the study and the majority of computational analysis.

- o **Wasserman Lab:** 'Cis-regulatory mechanisms of gene expression alterations in B cell lymphomas' I developed and applied methods to predict the effect of cis-regulatory somatic variants in B-cell lymphomas on transcription factor binding sites. These predictions were used by Dr. Anthony Mathelier and Calvin Lefebvre to associate regulatory variants with alterations in gene expression. This work was published in Genome Biology.
- Wasserman Lab (NSERC): 'Computational identification of transcription factor binding sites from whole-genome sequence data'

I developed computational methods to predict the effect of *cis*-regulatory variants within transcription factor binding sites on transcription factor binding affinity. The optimizations I introduced sped up the algorithm by 4-5 orders of magnitude, allowing for a single whole genome to be processed in a few hours. This method was used to generate the predictions in the MANTA database and its successor MANTA2 (published in *Scientific Data*).

Honours and Awards

o CGS — Michael Smith Foreign Study Supplement (\$6,000):	2018-2019
o Canadian Conference on Ovarian Cancer Research Oral Presentation Award (\$200):	2018
o Canadian Conference on Ovarian Cancer Research Travel Award (\$500):	2018
o BIG Research Day Poster Presentation Award (\$50):	2018
o Sing Tao Ambassador Award, Top 10:	2017
o CIHR Vanier Scholarship (\$50,000/year):	2016-2019
 UBC Four Year Fellowship (4YF, \$18,200/year): 	2016-2020
Elwyn Gregg Memorial Fellowship (\$5,000):	2015
Faculty of Science Graduate Award (\$3,236):	2015
o CIHR CGS-M Scholarship (\$17,500):	2015-2016
 Faculty of Medicine Graduate Award (\$4,072): 	2014
Faculty of Science Graduate Award (\$3,407):	2014

0	CFRI Summer Student Scholarship (\$3,750):	2014
0	BC Children's Hospital Research-CIHR-UBC MD/PhD Scholarship (\$21,000/year):	2013-2021
0	Ward-Essof Scholarship (\$965):	2013
0	Pacific Blue Cross Medical Entrance Scholarship (\$1,000):	2013
0	BC Clinical Genomics Network Training Award (\$3,750):	2013
0	Charles and Jane Banks Scholarship (\$1,000):	2013
0	UBC Trek Excellence Scholarship (\$1,500):	2012
0	NSERC Summer Studentship (\$4,500):	2012
0	UBC Trek Excellence Scholarship (\$1,500):	2011
0	Larry Roberts Science One Memorial Scholarship (\$1,000):	2011
0	Janusz J. Klawe Memorial Science One Scholarship (\$900):	2010
0	J. Fred Muir Memorial Scholarship in Science (\$1,000):	2010
0	President's Entrance Scholarship (\$2,500):	2010
0	British Columbia Government Scholarship (\$1,000):	2010
0	Passport to Education (\$500):	2010
0	3rd place in BC, Euclid Mathematics Contest (\$1,000):	2010
0	1st place, BC's Brightest Minds Physics Competition (\$1,500):	2010
0	1st place in BC, Michael Smith Science Challenge (\$100):	2009
0	Genome BC Award (\$50):	2009

Publications

2018: **Allen W. Zhang**, Andrew McPherson, Katy Milne, David R. Kroeger, Phineas T. Hamilton, Alex Miranda et al. Interfaces of Malignant and Immunologic Clonal Dynamics in Ovarian Cancer. *Cell*, 173(7):1755–1769.e22, jun 2018.

: Alex Miranda, Phineas T Hamilton, **Allen W Zhang**, Etienne Becht, Artur Mezheyeuski, Jarle Bruun et al. Cancer stemness, intratumoral heterogeneity, and immune response across cancers. *bioRxiv*, page 352559, jun 2018.

: Tyler Funnell, **Allen Zhang**, Yu-Jia Shiah, Diljot Grewal, Robert Lesurf, Steven McKinney et al. Integrated single-nucleotide and structural variation signatures of DNA-repair deficient human cancers. *bioRxiv*, 267500, feb 2018.

: Rebecca A.G. De Souza, Natalia Kosior, Sarah B. Thomson, Anthony Mathelier, **Allen W. Zhang**, Kristina Bečanović et al. Computational Analysis of Transcriptional Regulation Sites at the HTT Gene Locus. *Journal of Huntington's Disease*, 7(3):223–237, jul 2018.

: Yi Kan Wang, Ali Bashashati, Michael S Anglesio, Dawn R Cochrane, Diljot S Grewal, Gavin Ha et al. Genomic consequences of aberrant DNA repair mechanisms stratify ovarian cancer histotypes. *Nature Genetics*, apr 2017.

: Puya Seid-Karbasi, Xin C. Ye, **Allen W. Zhang**, Nicole Gladish, Suzanne Y. S. Cheng, Katharina Rothe et al. CuboCube: Student creation of a cancer genetics e-textbook using open-access software for social learning. *PLOS Biology*, 15(3):e2001192, mar 2017.

: Andrew McPherson, Andrew Roth, Emma Laks, Tehmina Masud, Ali Bashashati, **Allen W Zhang** et al. Divergent modes of clonal spread and intraperitoneal mixing in high-grade serous ovarian cancer. *Nature Genetics*, 48(7):758–767, may 2016.

: A. Mathelier, O. Fornes, D.J. Arenillas, C.-Y. Chen, G. Denay, J. Lee et al. JASPAR 2016: A major expansion and update of the open-access database of transcription factor binding profiles. *Nucleic Acids Research*, 44(D1), 2016.

2015: A. Mathelier, C. Lefebvre, A.W. Zhang, D.J. Arenillas, J. Ding, W.W. Wasserman et al. Cis-regulatory

somatic mutations and gene-expression alteration in B-cell lymphomas. Genome Biology, 16(1), 2015.

2014: A. Mathelier, X. Zhao, **A.W. Zhang**, F. Parcy, R. Worsley-Hunt, D.J. Arenillas et al. JASPAR 2014: An extensively expanded and updated open-access database of transcription factor binding profiles. *Nucleic Acids Research*, 42(D1), 2014.

News Releases

"Arms race" between cancer and immune system revealed

Vancouver. Canada

BC Cancer & UBC Medicine

May 2018

An injection of youth

Vancouver, Canada

UBC Medicine

September 2014

https://www.med.ubc.ca/an-injection-of-youth/

Presentations

Systems Genetics of Cancer 2018

Portland, USA

Oral presentation (chalk talk)

June 2018

Interfaces of malignant and immunologic clonal dynamics in ovarian cancer

Canadian Conference for Ovarian Cancer Research 2018

Edmonton, Canada

Oral presentation (3rd place)

May 2018

The Evolutionary Interplay Between Lymphocytes and Cancer Cells in High-Grade Serous Ovarian Cancer

BIG Research Day 2018

Vancouver, Canada

Poster presentation (3rd place)

March 2018

The evolutionary interplay between lymphocytes and cancer cells in high-grade serous ovarian cancer

Friesen Award Laureate Institutional Visit

Vancouver, Canada

Oral presentation (invited)

January 2018

The malignant-immune interface in high-grade serous ovarian cancer

Canadian Cancer Research Conference 2017

Vancouver, Canada

Oral presentation

November 2017

Spatiotemporal dynamics of tumour-infiltrating lymphocytes, mutational scars, and cancer clones in high-grade serous ovarian cancer

BC Tech Summit 2017

Vancouver, Canada

Oral and poster presentation (invited)

March 2017

Profiling clonal diversity at the single-cell level & the effect of immune cells on tumour evolution in high-grade serous ovarian cancer

16th Annual Bellairs Workshop: Cancer and the Immune System

Holetown, Barbados

January 2017

Oral presentation (invited)

Tumour infiltrating lymphocytes and clonal evolution in high-grade serous ovarian cancer

AACR Annual General Meeting 2016

New Orleans, Louisiana

Poster presentation

April 2016

Properties of the immune microenvironment associated with clonal diversity in high-grade serous ovarian cancer

Clinician-Investigator Trainee Association of Canada AGM 2015

Toronto, Canada

Poster presentation

November 2015

Co-evolution of tumour-infiltrating lymphocytes and cancer clones in high-grade serous ovarian cancer

BC Children's Hospital Research Poster Day

Poster presentation

Vancouver, Canada July 2014

BC Children's Hospital Research Poster Day

Vancouver, Canada

Poster presentation

July 2013

BC Children's Hospital Research Poster Day

Vancouver, Canada

Poster presentation

July 2012

Technical and Personal skills

Programming Languages/Tools

Proficient in: R (+ Rmarkdown, Shiny), Python (+ Jupyter), TeX (+ beamer), Perl, bash

Competent with: C, C++, cwl, RevBayes, SQL

Basic ability with: Julia, Matlab, Javascript, Java, HTML

O Tools:

Environments: Linux, snakemake, make, git, conda, docker, singularity Model development and machine learning: pymc3, tensorflow, theano

o Other Software Skills: MS Word, Powerpoint, Excel, Adobe Illustrator, InDesign, Inkscape

Interests and extra-curricular activity

Violinist Vancouver, Canada

Performer's ARCT level (w/ Grade 10 theory requirements)

I have played the violin for 10+ years. I enjoy playing classical music (orchestral pieces and unaccompanied Bach) and trained under Amy Paster Levinson. I was a member of the Sizzlers Fiddle Group; during my time with the group we recorded 2 CDs, went on tours to Canada's East Coast (Halifax, Charlottetown, Fredericton), Victoria, and Seattle, and performed at the Vancouver Fringe Festival.

Genetics in Medicine Club

Vancouver, Canada

Executive, Co-founder

May 2015-December 2017

I helped develop the Genetics in Medicine seminar series. The goal of our seminar series was to enrich genetics education for medical students by inviting speakers that apply principles classical genetics and modern genomics in their everyday clinical practice or research.

Skin Cancer Awareness Network (SCAN)

Vancouver, Canada

Co-founder, Events Co-ordinator

May 2014-September 2015

I helped organize public events in Vancouver and presentations at secondary schools and community centres around the Lower Mainland to highlight skin care promotion and skin cancer awareness. I also trained undergraduate student volunteers and undergraduate student leaders (USLs) for presentations at secondary schools. I helped apply for and secure **UBC Teaching and Learning Enhancement Funding** (TLEF) as part of an initiative to create an open-access e-book to provide access to clinically relevant dermatology knowledge for medical students.

Adams Lab (UBC)

Vancouver, Canada

Research Student

June 2013-August 2013

I devised algorithms for analyzing *cis*-regulatory alterations in *Arabidopsis thaliana* with Dr. Keith Adams. The focus of this research was to study regulatory element evolution following genomic duplication events.

Imagine UBC

Vancouver, Canada

Science Squad Manager

January 2013-September 2013

I worked closely with a Science Squad Leader to train 8 Imagine UBC MUG Leaders for Imagine Day in September 2013. Worked with MUG Leaders to develop icebreaker activities, and led workshops on conflict resolution, teamwork, and campus tours. Each MUG Leader was responsible for supervising a group of 8-10 incoming UBC students.

The Fair Haven United Church Homes

Vancouver, Canada

Graphics Designer

July 2012-May 2013

I re-designed the resident booklet for senior home visitors and residents as a volunteer.

Richmond General Hospital

Richmond, Canada

Emergency Department Volunteer

July 2012-May 2013

I delivered meals and blankets to patients, interacted with patients and visitors in the waiting room, and assisted with wayfinding.

UBC Math Circle Vancouver, Canada

Volunteer Leader

January 2012-April 2014

I served as an undergraduate leader for the UBC Math Circle, a group of mathematically-talented high school students selected by UBC professor Dr. George Bluman based on performance in national math competitions. I had participated in this group as a high school student (2010), and was nominated as a Leader in 2012 by Dr. Joel Feldman based on performance in MATH 226 (Honours Multivariable Calculus). I helped develop problem sets, led students through problems, and arranged for faculty speakers.

Gordon Lab Vancouver, Canada

Undergraduate Volunteer

April 2011-December 2011

I helped cross and propagate *Drosophila melanogaster* lines for neurobiological studies in Dr. Mike Gordon's lab at the Life Sciences Institute.

Mathematics and Physics Tutoring

Vancouver, Canada

Private Tutor

June 2010-April 2014

I tutored 2 students in Mathematics and Physics 11 and 12, along with AP Calculus BC.

Amati String Studio

Vancouver, Canada

Website Designer

June 2007-August 2013

I designed and maintained the websites www.amatistringstudio.ca and www.sizzlersfiddlegroup.org.